Guide to the Ulysses Kay papers,
Rare Book and Manuscript Library Columbia University Libraries
- Series IX: Audiovisual Materials, 1947-1988 undated
  - Subseries IX.1: Audio Recordings, 1947-1988 undated
    - Untitled, undated, (1 7-inch reel) (Box 106)
      (The reel is not labeled, but there are notecards in the box on what appears to be "Jubilee")
    - "The Juggler of Our Lady," 1962 February23, (1 7-inch reel, 7.5 ips) (Box 106)
      (World Premiere at Xavier University, New Orleans, Louisiana. Richard Harrison, conductor. Mervin Wallace, tenor. Xavier University Opera Workshop.)
    - "Juggler of Our Lady," undated (Box 104)
    - Kay, undated, (1 audiocassette) (Box 104)
      ( Includes "Of New Horizons," "Sinfonia in E," "A Short Overture," "Markings," "Serenade for Orchestra", and "Umbrian Scene")
    - Kay, 1983, (2 audiocassettes) (Box 105)
    - Kay Concert Part I and II, undated, (2 7-inch reels, 7.5 ips) (Box 106)
      (Includes "Brief Elegy" for oboe and piano, "Triptych on the Texts of Blake" for Soprano, Vln, Vc, and Pfe, "Suite for Flute and Oboe," and "Choral Triptych" )
    - Lehman Talk, 1973 November 22, (1 7-inch reel, 7.5 ips) (Box 106)
      Content of the reel has been digitized by Columbia University Libraries' Digital and Preservation Division, under the file name root: RBML_UlyssesKayPapers_7341105_LehmanCollege_19731122
    - Lament for April 15 and Other Modern Madrigals, The Randolph Singers, Composers Recording Inc. CRI-102, 1956 or later, (1 33 1/3 rpm phonograph record) (Box 109 A)
      (Includes Kay’s "How Stands the Glass AroundÀ" and "What’s in a NameÀ")
    - "The Land" (NBC News), 1962 February19, (1 7-inch reel, 7.5 ips) (Box 106)
      (Music only)
    - "The Land," 1962 February19, (1 33 1/3 rpm acetate phonograph disc) (Box 110)
      (Produced by NBC. Music only.)
    - Lincoln, Illinois Centennial, 1953 September 1, (2 5-inch reels) (Box 108)
      (Includes "A Lincoln Letter")
    - Louisville Orchestra First Edition Records, Robert Whitney, conductor, First Edition Records LOU-545-8, circa 1948-1960, (1 33 1/3 rpm phonographic record) (Box 109 B)
      (Includes Kay’s "Serenade for Orchestra")
    - Louisville Orchestra First Edition Records, Robert Whitney, conductor, First Edition Records LOU-651, After 1964, (1 33 1/3 rpm phonographic record) (Box 109 B)
      (Includes Kay’s "Umbrian Scene")
    - "Markings," 1967 April 16, (1 7-inch reel, 7.5 ips) (Box 107)
      (WQXR broadcast of the Cleveland Orchestra)
    - "Markings," 1978 September 29, (1 7-inch reel, 7.5 ips) (Box 107)
    - "Markings" (Kay) and "Study No. 3" (SydermanÀ), 1979, (1 7-inch reel, 7.5 ips) (Box 107)
      (Kay’s piece is performed by the New York Philharmonic,1979 Broadcast)
    - "Markings," undated, (1 33 1/3 rpm acetate phonograph record. Record has some signs of deterioration.) (Box 111)
    - MU 10644 undated, (1 7-inch reel, 7.5 ips) (Box 107)
      (Includes "A Short Overture" for orchestra and "Triptych on Texts of Blake" for soprano, violin, cello, and piano)
    - National Public Radio (NPR) Interview with Ulysses Kay, 1988, (1 7-inch reel) (Box 107)
      Content of the reel has been digitized by Columbia University Libraries' Digital and Preservation Division, under the file name root: RBML_UlyssesKayPapers_7341105_NPRinterview_19880000
    - North Texas State University School of Music, 1971 July 1, (1 10.5-inch reel) (Box 107)
      (Includes and "Parables" and possibly "Facets")
    - "Nosotros" for United Nations film for Latin America. Music by Ulysses Kay, 1962 August, (1 33 1/3 rpm acetate phonograph record) (Box 110)
    - "Of New Horizons," undated, (1 7-inch reel) (Box 107)
    - "Of New Horizons," undated, (1 7-inch reel) (Box 114)
      Chicago Symphony
    - "Of New Horizons" undated, (1 7-inch reel) (Box 107)
      (Cleveland Orchestra. Irvin Hoffman.)
    - "[Of] New Horizons" Columbus Philharmonic, Izler Solomon, conductor, 1947 March4, (1 acetate phonograph record. Record shows signs of deterioration.) (Box 111)
      (The label on the sleeve states "Quintet for Flute and "Strings" but the label on the record indicates this is "New Horizons")
    - "Once There was a Man," undated, (1 7-inch reel, 7.5 ips) (Box 107)
    - Opus One Number 35, Ruth Norman, piano, Recorded at Catholic University, 1977 April 26, (1 33 1/3 rpm phonograph record) (Box 109 B)
      (Includes Kay’s "Invention III")
      (4 copies)
    - Penn State, 1980 May 2, (1 7-inch reel, 7.5 ips) (Box 107)
    - Penn State, 1980 May 3, (1 7-inch reel, 7.5 ips) (Box 107)
    - "Pieta," undated, (1 audiocassette) (Box 105)
      (American Composers Orchestra)
    - "Pieta" and "Suite for Band," undated, (1 5-inch reel, 7.5 ips) (Box 108)
    - "Portraits," 1964 April 22, (1 7-inch reel, 7.5 ips) (Box 107)
      (Erie Philharmonic. James Simple, conductor. Premiere Performance.)
    - "Presidential Suite," undated, (1 audiocassette) (Box 105)
      (St. Joseph’s Symphony), undated
    - "The Quiet One," 1960 July 25, (1 7-inch reel, 7.5 ips) (Box 107)
      (Transferred from 78 records)
    - "Quintet Concerto," undated, (1 7-inch reel, 7.5 ips) (Box 107)
      (Juilliard School Orchestra)
    - Roosevelt Show, 1958 March19, (1 7-inch reel, 7.5 ips) (Box 107)
      (CBS Orchestra. Antonini, conductor. Includes "FDR". See Also: "FDR" on acetate disc.)
    - "Scherzi Musicali," 1973 November 11, (1 7-inch reel, 7.5 ips) (Box 107)
      (Carnegie-Mellon University Orchestra. Chauncey Kelley, conductor. Also includes Haydn’s "Symphony in E-Flat")
    - New Tape: "Scherzo-Serenade" for Orchestra and "Umbrian Scene," undated, (1 7-inch reel) (Box 114)
      (Out-takes)
    - "Serenade for Orchestra" The Louisville Orchestra, Robert Whitney, conductor, 1954 September 18, (1 78 rpm acetate phonograph record. Record shows signs of deterioration. The original tape was distorted, and this is reflected on this acetate disc.) (Box 111)
    - "Serenade for Orchestra," 1968 April 21, (1 7-inch reel) (Box 107)
      (Cornell Symphony Orchestra. Karol Husa, conductor.)
    - "A Short Overture," undated, (1 7-inch reel) (Box 107)
      (Queens Symphony Orchestra. 200th Concert. David Katz, Music Director.)
    - Skidmore College, circa 1975, (2 7-inch reels, 7.5 ips) (Box 107)
      (Includes "Triptych on Texts of Blake," "Five Portraits," "Tears, Flow No More," "Two Dunbar Lyrics," "What’s In A Name?" "How Stands the Glass Around?" and "Brief Elegy.")
    - Smithsonian: Black American Composer #4 (4 of 4), undated, (1 audiocassette) (Box 105)
    - "Song of Ahab" George Irving, baritone, Milton Rosenstock, conductor, undated, (1 33 1/3 rpm acetate phonograph record) (Box 110)
    - South Carolina State College (SCSC): Kay Seminar, 1968 May 9, (1 5-inch reel) (Box 108)
    - Southern Connecticut State University, 1968 May 9, (1 7-inch reel, 7.5 ips) (Box 107)
      (Includes "Brief Elegy," "Triptych on Texts of Blake," and "Suite for Flute and Oboe".)
    - "String Quartet" National Gallery Orchestra, Richard Bales, conductor, 1953 May 24, (1 33 1/3 acetate phonograph record) (Box 110)
    - "String Quartet No. 3," 1962 April 2, (1 7-inch reel, 7.5 ips) (Box 107)
      (Stanley String Quartet)
    - "String Quartet No. 3, 1964, (1 7-inch reel) (Box 107)
      (Also includes Binkerd’s "String Quartet #2")
    - "String Quartet No. 3," undated, (1 7-inch reel) (Box 107)
      (Composer’s Forum)
    - "Submarine," 1959 March26, (1 33 1/3 rpm acetate phonograph record. Record shows signs of deterioration.) (Box 111)
      (Produced by 20th Century Past CBS)
    - "Suite for Orchestra" Radio Italiana, Concerto Dean Dixon, Torino, 1952 August 1, (4 33 1/3 rpm acetate phonograph records. All discs show signs of deterioration.) (Box 111)
    - "Suite for Orchestra, undated, (1 33 1/3 acetate phonograph record) (Box 110)
    - "Swiss Shapes," 1961 January 16, (1 5-inch reel, 7.5 ips) (Box 108)
      (Composite music only)
    - "Swiss Shapes," 1961 January 16, (1 33 1/3 rpm phonograph record) (Box 110)
    - "Swiss Watches," 1959 December 11, (1 33 1/3 acetate phonograph record) (Box 110)
      (Cut 1: 2 min. Cut 2: Mens Cut 3: Ladies)
    - "Swiss Watches," undated, (1 33 1/3 acetate phonograph record) (Box 110)
      (ANNCR. Tracks and Orchestra Tracks. Produced by Cunningham and Walsh, Inc.)
    - "Symphony No. 1," 1974 March, (1 7-inch reel) (Box 107)
      (Julliard Orchestra. James Conlon, conductor.)
    - "Theater Set," undated, (1 7-inch reel, 7.5 ips) (Box 107)
      (Robert Shaw and Cleveland Orchestra)
    - "Theme," 1962 September 5 (Box 108)
    - Thomas Harmon Plays American Organ Music of Three Centuries on the Schoenberg Hall and Royce Hall Organs, University of California at Los Angeles (UCLA), Orion ORS 76255 circa 1976, (1 33 1/3 rpm phonograph record) (Box 109 B)
      (2 copies, one copy is inscribed to Kay by Thomas Harmon. Includes Kay’s "Organ Suite No. 1")
    - "Three Musketeers" TV Music, 1960 November 25, (1 33 1/3 rpm acetate phonograph record) (Box 110)
      (Hotchkiss Music)
    - "Trigon" and "Of New Horizons," 1961 and 1967 May 15, (1 7-inch reel) (Box 107)
      ("Trigon" was recorded at an outdoor rehearsal in 1961. "Of New Horizons" was performed by the Seattle Youth Orchestra on May 15, 1967.)
    - TV and Commercial Cues and Music, undated, (1 33 1/3 rpm acetate phonograph record) (Box 110)
    - "Two Impromptus," 1987 February8, (4 audiocassettes) (Box 105)
      (Marcantonio Barone, piano)
    - "Umbrian Scene," circa 1964 March, (1 5-inch reel, 7.5 ips) (Box 108)
      (New Orleans Philharmonic. Werner Torkanowsky, conductor.)
    - The United Church on the Green Sings Praises, Recorded on May 9 and June 13, 1981 at United Church on the Green, New Haven, Connecticut, Vogt Recording Company CSRV 2691 1981, (1 33 1/3 rpm phonograph record) (Box 109 B)
      (Includes Kay’s "O Praise the Lord")
    - A Recording of Music by the Graduates of the University of Arizona, University of Arizona College of Fine Arts School of Music, 100th Anniversary 1862 Land Grant College and University System, 1962, (1 33 1/3 rpm phonograph record) (Box 109 B)
      (Includes Kay’s "Of New Horizons")
    - University of Arizona, undated, (1 5-inch reel) (Box 108)
    - University of Illinois, 1959 November 5, (2 7-inch reels, 7.5 ips) (Box 107)
      (Includes "Fugitive Songs," "Second String Quartet," "Serenade No. 2" for four horns in F. )
    - University of Missouri-Kansas City (UMKC) Conservatory of Music Black Music Festival: Kay "Convocation," 1981 November 6, (1 audiocassette) (Box 105)
    - University of Missouri-Kansas City (UMKC) Conservatory of Music Black Music Festival: Kay "On Composing," 1981 November 13, (1 audiocassette) (Box 105)
    - Urban League: Ulysses Kay, Leonard de Paur, 1954 January 6, (1 7-inch reel, 3 3/4 ips) (Box 107)
      Content of the reel has been digitized by Columbia University Libraries' Digital and Preservation Division, under the file name root: RBML_UlyssesKayPapers_7341105_UrbanLeagueLeonardDePaur_19540106
    - Urban League: Ulysses Kay, Ray Felix, November 4, (1 5-inch reel, 7.5 ips) (Box 108)
      Content of the reel has been digitized by Columbia University Libraries' Digital and Preservation Division, under the file name root: RBML_UlyssesKayPapers_7341105_UrbanLeagueRayFelix
    - Ussachevsky Translation, 1954 July 23 (Box 107)
    - "The Western Paradise," 1976 October, (1 7-inch reel) (Box 107)
      (The National Symphony Orchestra. Carnegie Hall. Antal Dorati, conductor. William Conrad, narrator.)
    - "The Western Paradise" for Narrator and Orchestra, circa 1977, (1 7-inch reel) (Box 107)
      (The National Symphony Orchestra. Antal Dorati, conductor, William Conrad, narrator. This appears to have been broadcast as part of "International Concert Hall" #770123 on National Public Radio. )
    - "The Western Paradise," undated, (1 audiocassette) (Box 105)
    - WMHT FM Schenectady, New York, Music America "In Conversation with Ulysses Kay," undated, (1 7-inch reel) (Box 107)
      Content of the reel has been digitized by Columbia University Libraries' Digital and Preservation Division, under the file name root: RBML_UlyssesKayPapers_7341105_InConversationWithUKay
    - Unknown, circa 1954-1964, (1 7-inch reel) (Box 107)
      (This reel was re-used and it is unclear what is on the reel. It May consist entirely of material by other persons. It May also include material from the Urban League from March3, 1954)
    - Unlabeled, undated, (1 10.5-inch reel) (Box 107)
    - Unlabeled, undated, (2 33 1/3 rpm acetate phonograph records. Both records show signs of deterioration.) (Box 111)
  - Series IX.2: Video, 1959 undated
    There is very little video in the collection. There is one video recording from the Urban League, and three film reels of watch commercials that used Kay’s music.
    - Film: Commercials
      - "Quality Spot," 1959 September 11, (1 4-inch reel) (Box 108)
      - "Man’s Watch," 1959 October 8, (1 4-inch reel) (Box 108)
      - "Woman’s Watch," 1959 October 8, (1 4-inch reel) (Box 108)
    - Urban League "Ulysses Kay," undated, (1 U-matic videocassette) (Box 108)
- Series X: Barbara Kay Files, circa 1955-1991
  This series consists of a small amount of material kept by Barbara Kay. These files contain a calendar, correspondence, and a few photographs. The files also contain materials related to the civil rights movement, including pamphlets, material on issues related to Englewood, New Jersey, and materials related to the Congress of Racial Equality (CORE).
  - Calendar, 1956 (Box 81, Folder 13)
  - Correspondence--General
    - circa 1955 (Box 81, Folder 14)
    - 1991 (Box 81, Folder 15)
  - Correspondence, Addresses, Etc., circa 1961-1962 (Box 81, Folder 16)
  - Papers
    - circa 1962 (Box 81, Folder 17)
    - circa 1962-1965 (Box 82, Folder 1 to 3)
  - Photographs, 1991 (Box 82, Folder 4)
    (Unidentified)
- Series XI: Annotated, Inscribed, and Signed Materials, circa 1947-1986
  This series contains materials that are annotated by Kay as well as materials that are either signed or inscribed to either Ulysses Kay or to someone in the Kay family. The materials include inscriptions from authors, composers, conductors, musicians, and family members. The series also includes a small number of annotated scores and The Norton Scores: An Anthology for Listening.
  - Subseries XI.1: Recordings, 1958 1984-1986
    This subseries consists of four inscribed phonograph records. Two of these are from musicians Cecil Lytle and Wanda Maximilien, the others are from Gennady Rozdesventsky and Tikhon Khrennikov, both of whom were part of the composers exchange in Moscow in 1958.
    - Cecil Lytle, "The Scriabin Series, Volume 1," Klavier Records KD 7032 1986, (1 33 1/3 rpm phonograph record) (Box 109 B)
      (Inscribed to Ulysses Kay by Cecil Lytle)
    - Wanda Maximilien, "Wanda Maximilien Plays Shapey’s ’21 Variations’, Chenoweth’s ‘Three Musics’ and Moevs ‘Una Collara’," Composers Recordings, Inc. CRI DC 496, 1984, (1 33 1/3 rpm phonograph record) (Box 109 B)
      (Inscribed to Hillary Kay by Wanda Maximilien)
    - Moscow State Symphony Orchestra, 1957 (Box 109 B)
      (Inscribed to Ulysses Kay by Gennady Rozdesventsky, Conductor of the Moscow State Symphony Orchestra, Moscow, October 15, 1958. Inscription is in English. Album information is in Russian.)
    - Tikhon Khrennikov, 1955 (Box 109 B)
      (The album contains Khrennikov’s compositions. Inscribed to Ulysses Kay by the composer, 1958. The album information and the inscription are in Russian.)
  - Subseries XI.2: Scores, circa 1947-1972 undated
    This series includes fifteen scores. Of these, about half have some annotations. Of the others scores, six are signed or inscribed by the composer or the lyricist, one is inscribed by Barbara Kay, and another is inscribed by J.G.R.
    - Alban Berg, "Sieben Frühe Lieder," 1907 (Box 112)
      (Inscribed to Ulysses Kay by his wife, Barbara Kay, 1951)
    - Alban Berg, "Wozzeck," Universal Edition A.G. Wien, undated (Box 112)
      (Annotated)
    - Paul Chihara, "Kyrie Eleison," Dayton Ohio: The Heritage Music Press, 1971 (Box 112)
      (Piece is dedicated and inscribed to Ulysses Kay by the composer.)
    - Paul Chihara, "Magnificat," 1965 (Box 112)
      (Inscribed to Ulysses Kay by the composer.)
    - Luigi Dallapiccola, ""Quaderno Musicale di Annalibera," Milano: Edizioni Suvini Zerboni, circa 1954 (Box 112)
    - Ernest Kaye, "A Musical Crossword," Oxford University Press, 1961 (Box 112)
    - Gail Kubik, Second Choral Suite from "A Mirror for the Sky," New York: Ricordi, 1958 (Box 112)
      (Inscribed to Ulysses Kay by the composer, 1958)
    - Arnold Schoenberg, "Phantasy" Opus 47, New York: C.F. Peters Corporation, 1952 (Box 112)
    - Arnold Schoenberg, "Five Pieces for Orchestra" Opus 16, New York: C.F. Peters Corporation, 1952 (Box 112)
    - William Schuman, "Concerto for Violin and Orchestra," Bryn Mawr, Pennsylvania: Merion Music, Inc., 1960 (Box 112)
    - Roger Sessions, "Idyll of Theocritus," New York: Edward B. Marks Music Corporation, circa 1957 (Box 112)
      (Inscribed to "Oliver, in cordial friendship" by the composer, New York, September, 1957)
    - Jean Sibelius, "Symphony No. 3" Opus 52, New York: E.F. Kalmus Orchestra Scores, 1933 (Box 112)
    - Igor Stravinsky, "Petroushka," New York: E.F. Kalmus Orchestra Scores, 1933 (Box 112)
    - Igor Stravinsky, "Greeting Prelude" for the eightieth birthday of Pierre Monteux, London: Boosey & Hawkes, 1955 (Box 112)
      (Full score; inscribed to Ulysses Kay from J.G.R., March 1972)
    - Kurt Weill, "Street Scene," Chappell & Co. Inc., circa 1947 (Box 112)
      (Music by Kurt Weill, book by Elmer Rice, and lyrics by Langston Hughes. Inscribed to Ulysses Kay by Langston Hughes.)
  - Subseries XI.3: Books, circa 1953-1983
    This subseries contains both inscribed and annotated books. Of these, only one is annotated: The Norton Scores: An Anthology for Listening. The others books are primarily inscribed by family or friends, with the exception of Stokowski: A Counterpoint of View, which is inscribed by its author Oliver Daniel.
    - R.O. Blechman, The Juggler of Our Lady: A Medieval Legend adapted by R.O. Blechman. New York: Henry Holt and Company, 1953 (Box 113)
      (Inscribed to Ulysses Kay by John H.)
    - Derek Brewer, Chaucer and His World. New York: Dodd, Mead & Company, 1978 (Box 113)
      (Inscribed to Ulysses and Barbara Kay, June, 1980 by "Oliver" who appears to be author Oliver Daniel-see also the inscription on the Oliver Daniel’s book in this series.)
    - Oliver Daniel, Stokowski: A Counterpoint of View. New York: Dodd, Mead & Company, 1982 (Box 113)
      (Inscribed to Ulysses and Barbara Kay by the author, March1, 1983.)
    - Curtis Harnack, We Have All Gone Away. Ames, Iowa: Iowa State University Press, 1981 (Box 113)
      (Inscribed to Barbara Kay by Ulysses Kay, Christmas, 1981)
    - Roger Kamien, editor. The Norton Scores: An Anthology for Listening. 3rd edition. New York: W.W. Norton & Company, Inc., 1977 (Box 113)
    - Virginia E. Kay, "Custom, Ideology and Propaganda: A Cultural History of Apartheid." PhD Diss., University of Chicago, 1978 (Box 113)
      (Inscribed to Barbara and Ulysses Kay by Virginia Kay.)
    - Claude Lévi-Strauss, Tristes Tropiques. New York: Atheneum, 1974 (Box 113)
      (Inscribed to Ulysses Kay by Virginia Kay, Christmas 1974)
    - Arnold J. Toynbee and Daisaku Ikeda, The Toynbee-Ikeda Dialogue: Man Himself Must Choose. Toyko: Kodansha International Ltd., 1976 (Box 113)
      (Inscribed to Ulysses Kay by Melinda Kay, December, 1980.)
    - Who is Who in Music. 5th edition. Myrtle Beach: Who is Who in Music, Inc., Ltd., 1951 (Box 113)
      (Inscribed to Ulysses Kay by Aunt Vic and Gladys, May, 1951. The volume includes an entry and photograph for Ulysses Kay.)